welcome to the stoa
the stoa is a digital campfire where we
cohere
and dialogue about what matters most at
the knife's edge
of what's happening now
hi everybody welcome to the stoa the
stoa is a digital campfire where we
gather to coherent dialogue
at the knife's edge of what matters most
and today
is the third of a series that we're
doing with samoa berger
i think i have that right called live
players
so uh we'll be doing a talk followed by
a q a
and uh with that i hand it over to samo
thanks for being here uh thank you for
having me as always
and uh yeah like the series and
the series is entitled live players and
one of the more interesting things and
the interesting implications
is where would we actually go
next in just a second
surprisingly warm day
so the question is where would we go
next were there live players who wanted
to
properly reform our institutions and
reorganize our society what might that
look like
and i think that one of the very basic
changes i
think we should see at almost every
level of society
is to have dominance of individuals
rather than of systems
so the presence and the ability to
express the actions of coherent minds
rather than adhering to
processes and protocols that were set
into place not even that long ago
chesterton's fence applies to a fence
that's been there for 500 years
it does not apply to something that's
been there for 50 years or
20 years a lot of the bureaucratic red
tape we've become
so used to is stuff that's only been
developed in the last 20
or 50 years a lot of the ideologies that
propose
that you know human individual action is
unimportant or
irrelevant or inappropriate or that
unusual
thinking or that you know extraordinary
changes in a person's life are unheard
of
this seems like it's been there since
time immemorial but i actually think
it is ratcheted up over the last 40
years
possibly starting as early as the middle
of the 20th century
possibly later in like the 1970s but
i think you know i think 40 years is
probably the best approximation and i
think it tracks
fairly naturally a different statistic
you can
map the distance that children are
allowed to roam
under on their own unsupervised by
parents
from the home throughout the 20th
century you start with
this vast radius of 20 miles it shrinks
to 5 miles
it shrinks to 1 mile and today it's like
100 feet
right so if you're a miner you're a kid
you on average
aren't allowed to go more than 100 feet
from your home i think we're approaching
conditions of home arrest
and home arrest together with school
arrest
means that these are you know fully
incarcerated human beings
i think this shows up in the adults as
well i think the adults have
less ability to roam now perhaps they
can you know
hop on a plane they can well at least
they could until 2020
and they go very far in terms of miles
but they don't go very far
in terms of cultures you fly 4 000 miles
you visit europe you visit north africa
southeast asia
and you never left a hotel right you're
always there in the simulated experience
of an identical culture
so i think the affordance to go into a
different mode of living
and come back from it to the midstream
switch careers
and break the tracking pattern i think
that's become
much harder now than 30 40 or 50 years
ago
i also think that there's strong
evidence
that this kind of narrowing effect is
partially
driven by the development of the
panopticon
we're all building the panopticon
together right it's not the case that
we needed invasive intrusive
sort of like heavy-handed government
action it's just that we
freely gave the information to both
the recommendation engines that enable
consumerism and our general you know
pattern of consumerism so we were very
happy when
amazon read our information and gave us
better and better recommendations
we're very happy when the search engine
seems to work better we don't really
care if it tracks us
and on the other hand we want to project
this
image of the perfect the ideal self and
we share this very aggressively we in
fact want all our friends to see
when we talk to a prominent person when
we eat delicious food
when we are in beautiful nature or when
we are traveling you know those 5 000
miles to that beautiful hotel on the
other end of the world
that might as well just be a western
hotel in a western city
these are all part of this information
cloud we've released
and this also means that not only are we
socially observing each other
all the time forcing us to keep up
appearances in this way
we're previously in a urban environment
at least you could have retreated into
anonymity
here i have to give a minor concession
to you know previous life where
i think that private privacy as such has
always been a rare and luxury good
enjoyed by the minority of the
population it's kind of an anomaly of
the 19th and 20th century
or to be more generous for large urban
population centers they have always been
an anomaly where it was possible to
maintain
some privacy and some social anonymity
right allowing this kind of reinvention
however the social technology of
self-reinvention such as
things such as a religious conversion or
a festival right a festival like where
it's possible to
have essentially opposite day right in
medieval carnivals
people would make fun of the pope they
would make fun of kings they would make
fun even of saints
how in the world was that possible if
you're burning witches the rest of the
year
well that massive release valve right
that
allowed a lot of the same
experimentation
uh much as i think the amish called room
springer where
they have this period where you know
children are becoming
adults they've been raised in the amish
community this very you know insular
type of christianity
and they have their own language it's
not english i think it's called plato
deutsch i could be wrong here i might be
misremembering it
uh amish german and they of course don't
make use of certain technology so this
is a really big lifestyle change and
then there's a period where
the kids are allowed to go out into the
world that's not the amish world
and explore it and learn from it so in
this way the
the amish i think are not like supremely
advanced they're in some ways you know
i mean perhaps they're objectively
advanced but this is a throwback right
there used to be more things like this
can we imagine opposite day or a digital
carnival
like i think we're way too uncomfortable
for that i think we feel
much too precarious to make fun of our
idols or
imagine a day where democrats are
supposed to be republicans and
republicans are supposed to be democrats
online
like i think people are too inflexible
both internally
and interpersonally for that so the
narrowing range of the roaming of
children is
a symptom though also a cause right
but mostly a symptom of the narrowing
range of risks
we feel comfortable with because these
are again not fundamentally physical
risks in terms of physical risks
even with the coronavirus pandemic
we are right now much much physically
safer than hundred years ago
but i think we feel and project onto
these physical risks and we flee away
from the physical risks
because we become hypersensitive
hypersensitized to the social risks
and this kind of need
for a particular kind of social approval
and a very consistent life story
that we can present not just
bureaucratically which is an ancient
problem right
you always need it you know here's the
document that proves that i was
conscripted already you can't conscript
me again
here's the document that proves i paid
my taxes here's the deed to my father's
you know farm and so on that kind of
bureaucratic legibility we
we've always had that or rather um you
know we've had it for let's say 20 000
years
or 10 000 years i have a contrarian
thesis that actually we've had
writing uh for much longer than usually
acknowledged right
probably all the way to the end of the
last ice age
all the way from the end of the last ice
age but let's just
took take the the normal you know
consensus history view of 10 000 years
so
as long as we've had writing we have had
to impose bureaucratic legibility
on organic lives and
now uh we also have a narrative
compatibility where
because there's this record that anyone
can always mine for previous comments
and pictures we are
socially stuck to be much more legible
than even kind of the
the rural the the word of mouth history
that a village might uh engage with
right because
again social media mob and a village
they both might know you about equally
well or rather they can access the same
amount of information
but you are far less powerless
interfacing with the village
now agreed a village can probably also
just kill you
and for now a social media mob cannot
but you have very little power over the
social media mob
compared to the individual relationships
you could leverage in a village in a
village so
there's a social self-consistency
enforcement and then
finally there's like a national security
uh apparatus of significant weight
that's been fully assembled and i think
we'll just be
deployed to different political purposes
in the very near future
okay so a lot of topics dropped them all
there
i proposed a few mechanisms i'm happy to
now double click on whatever part of
that
seemed the most interesting and uh
possibly if there are questions that
stand out i can
answer them immediately
great so uh if you would like to put a
proposition or a question into the chat
i will then call your name and you can
ask your question directly to samo
and then we're kind of going to allow
for an etiquette of a back and forth
but uh one round of back and forth and
then we'll go to the next person
so we already have some
propositions and questions from from dan
dan would you like to unbeat yourself
i guess i didn't i didn't mean to be
speaking actually
i just was triggered by what i was
hearing and making comments
um
you mentioned something at some point
about uh
the digital environment playing a big
role
you know the development of digital
technology and social at least for
people under 25 i think it's a primary
component of socialization
um arguably for people under 35 that
already existed but
i think people between 35 and 25 grew up
in a world where
text-based pseudonyms were the main mode
of interaction i do post on forums you
would
send you know emails whatever right
and you didn't necessarily use your own
face as your avatar on a forum in the
early 2000s
yeah yeah and i'm thinking back to the
mid 90s when i was one of the first
people on the on the internet um
it was completely text-based you know
that that was before
any graphics were there um okay
i i can i can see that to some level
there there yes there is some
socialization there
but i would i would i would argue that
independent of that as a separate strain
even if we took that out i think that
there's been an increasing
bureaucratization
of organizations and an increasing
clamping
down by the elites in these institutions
and and a and a
an increasing fear of
the one who questions the ideology
even if only innocently
questions the i you know not even aware
of the danger of the question
right right and of course there's
there's you know a thousand points of
doctrine that you might get wrong
right or even hidden or inexplicit
doctrine
um so it's very easy to ask that that
accidental question
um i think that i think that's right
like i said i opened with about 40 years
now we've seen this
increasing escalation so that predates
the judge the digital world
um and i think that partially comes out
of well there's several competing
explanations right
i think there is eric weinstein's
explanation
of the embedded growth obligation where
he proposes that most of our
institutions be they universities or
companies
or even you know ultimately governments
were predicated on perpetual growth
and in the absence of this growth they
cannot deliver on the implicit promises
that they have
in the academic system this shows up
where most grad students
the the graduate student was originally
a program intending to prepare you for
work in academia
the vast majority of grad students will
never work in academia
after they're done with their stint in
grad school and after they've you know
performed their task as cheap lab labor
essentially or you know assistance to
the professor
and this is something he speaks about
very eloquently he wrote
a paper on the topic and he also talks
about like the economics of
knowledge work i think that certainly
contributes a different story is the
story of like ideological shift
uh you have a left-wing story and a
right-wing story on this
the left-wing story is about the slow
dominance of neo-liberalism that hollows
out all
ideological alternatives where things
are exposed over and over again to the
open market where
losses are socialized and profits are
privatized
and then the right-wing version of this
story is the world where there's been a
slow march through the institutions
where over time say critical theory has
been over applied
and has deconstructed the basic values
of society
in the absence of those values of those
traditional modes of behavior
what you're stuck with is this very
minor and
very tight rule uh rule adhering process
right where you're trying to write all
the rules for all the places where you
might encounter harm
right so a social conservative would say
argued that you know
campus rape culture is a natural
consequence
of uh sexual liberation on campus or
even
a more extreme conservative would just
say it's a consequence of having co-ed
colleges
right so because they would take a
pessimistic view on human nature
now again these are like three stories
now and i can easily tell two more
uh two more stories i would like to tell
which i actually think
i feel capture this fairly well and are
not necessarily incompatible
with the eric weinstein story i think
it's very i think it's very insightful
in its own right
one is the succession problem where i
think the people currently running
the set of elites sorry the current set
of elites that's running the current
institutions
are possibly on the older end baby
boomer generation a few might be silence
a lot of them are say very older gen x
range right if you look at the average
age of ceos it's around 50 years old
these aren't the people who built these
institutions in the first place so
often they just lack a lot of the tacit
knowledge needed to run this well
so the first story is one of outright
succession failure
where there's a failure in skill
succession and the second one i would
advance
is that of a centralized declining
empire this is from
empire theory you can read about it in
my document titled
great founder theory so a subset of
great founder theory
is empire theory mostly deals with power
dynamics
and i think there's been in a
centralized declining empire what
happens is
the center cannot produce novel
resources or novel growth
thereby can't redistribute surplus of
growth
thereby only redistributes
the resources that already are there
therefore
necessarily comes into conflict so the
center the high power in society comes
in conflict with the middle layer of
society
because they are constantly
expropriating the middle layer
and giving back to different parts of
the middle layer and sometimes use
low as this kind of like counter-measure
now high mid and low aren't like classes
here
in a marxist sense or in a classical
class analysis sense these are
power classes in the sense that you
might classify an organization or an
individual is high middle
or low right so again we're not you're
necessarily talking about individual
identities
um so i think these two kind of go hand
in hand you have
a succession failure that's then
followed by
an extractive mode of institutions that
then
because their legitimacy still rests in
this wildly
growing era of the 1920s to 1960s
uh they have as a story of legitimacy
uh this this uh growth narrative that's
no longer there
i think like people you know of the baby
boomer generation i think they believe
that they would live to see the
singularity i mean it's 2020.
where's the singularity right
singularity would be a straightforward
extrapolation
of what growth should have brought had
it continued from 1970 in a compounding
way
cool very happy to to go to the next
question i think i uh
hopefully that was is a solid answer
great thank you so really great question
from anish
would you like to mute yourself
yes
um should i read the question out
yes please okay all right
hi um so
give me a moment yeah so one thing uh
that somewhat surprised me
when i initially came to the us you know
i mean it wasn't immediate but over time
i started to notice it
um was that there seems to be a pretty
complete lack of what you would call
uh bucknellian social
uh occasions that are just you pointed
this out
uh like you said you know opposite day
or that kind of
reversal right i try i try to bring
closer
what carnival used to be than rather
what it is currently right people might
associate carnival right now with
venetian carnival where you know it's
masks
or with brazilian carnival which is
nudity and in a funny way like masks and
nudity well i'm from san francisco
that's just normal
right so it's not so i try to show how
subversive carnival actually was in a
medieval context
or possibly you know um uh what's
what is the term of homolysis i think
when
you have an adverse thing uh an adverse
social
yes thank you yeah um for example small
amounts of radiation are very good for
the body because they seem to activate
regenerative mechanisms in the body
similarly with autophagy and fasting
exactly so perhaps
even from a social conservative
perspective uh
the carnival and you know festivals were
actually extremely good things
so uh like i was surprised by the
complete lack of
i said one somewhat bucknellian social
occasions
um and second
uh the the dionysian aspect of um
culture among the people that i was
sorted into i mean probably
it might be an artifact of the group of
people that i was sorted into thanks to
the
route that i took to come to the us
which is you know upper middle class
professionals of the software type
um and um yeah
but what surprised me was that the the
image that one has of the us when you're
from outside
is a significantly more liberated and
less repressed place
as in less less every day regulated if
that makes sense
right um and do you think this has to do
with
like like you said people are extremely
afraid do you think it has to do with
the rejection of
what chapman would call inherent
nebulosity
as in it seems a lot of these
form the purpose of taking you know
boundaries which might have been
somewhat off perhaps and just
acknowledging their nebulosity in sort
of
providing an avenue like the carnivals
or the other things of this kind
renegotiating the fact that they are
nebulous and that they might slowly
change over time
and so something like this could
generate common knowledge
about um oh okay turns out that yes
in fact there has been some kind of a
minor shift like is that
maybe a neurosis or just uh
i think it is a it it is definitely a
narrowing of cultural space
i think it's very difficult to settle on
exactly the right ontology
well i greatly appreciate chapman's
writing i feel the ultimate
classification of belief systems
culture and values is yet to be written
and if we listened to hegel
we would also say it can never be
written as soon as you write it you need
to rewrite it and
you know kind of self-author in this
autopoetic way i think that
there is a fragilization
of communally
accepted principles on which to judge
conflict mediation right so conflict
mediation and conflict management is a
fact of the human condition
and i think there used to be a very rich
vocabulary of many different
principles you could invoke on
what grounds should we judge this
dispute and not even judge in a legal
sense just judge in a social sense in
fact
you know no matter how tolerant we are
we again we always stay judgmental kind
of as human beings
again maybe maybe my perspective is
someone from san francisco is a little
biased here where it's like
maximum tolerance and maximum
intolerance of a particular type go
very well together but it seems to me
that the vocabulary people can invoke or
even agree on when it's appropriate to
invoke has
shrunk which means fewer possible
outcomes means conflict resolution
less well-suited this means
ideological consensus has to be more
rigid office politics has to be more
rigid
so i almost would look for this in the
microdynamics of decision making
situations
then radiating outward to something like
the narrative rather than
the narrative you know infecting or
putting pressure on the micro
environment of a particular office
okay i mean my own experience in the bay
area is that
conflict resolution is almost completely
broken down and it generally turns
into a jockeying for greater victim
status and
everything eventually just degenerates
into this is probably abusive
and that's the end of it um so
thank you thank you thank you for your
question but we'll go for the next one
now
great thank you and we'll have
a scroll up here to shar
would you like to have it yourself sure
um hi
samuel um i wanted to ask as we see
globalization
well i'm not sure we can call it it's
receding but
uh as you see the cyanosphere increasing
and maybe a multi-polarity of the world
of course it's exaggerated the u.s is
still quite strong but still
do you see more uh possibilities of
uh diverse cultural spaces and an
expansion
of possibilities the you know like
not bring like the lack of you're
talking about just going to a similar
uh hotel you know it's all the same all
the design looks like starbucks and all
that stuff
but do you see that receding as
globalization changes
um i think that globalization is
actually here to stay in the following
sense
i think that we might see a receding of
the entanglement of the economic
uh you know security fundamentals of
different countries
we might see a receding in
the hyper centralization or
unified vision of the future so you
might have societies fragmented along
different visions of the future
but i think we won't see any reduction
in the following things i don't think we
will
um like how should i illustrate this
the european union might actually
politically fall apart
however the youth of individual european
countries have never been more similar
in their tastes and their habits of life
arguably
young europeans and young americans are
much more similar today
in their consumer habits and their
lifestyles than they were 40 years ago
right so europeans bought more cars
americans bought fewer cars
you know americans started drinking
belgian beer europeans started eating
more hamburgers
it kind of like mellowed out evened out
and i think by default what we're going
to see culturally
is a somewhat deglobalized world
because elite culture will i think
remain
focused on english but i think the
global internet will fragment first
along sovereign lines and secondly
along um linguistic lines i think
there'll be an english-speaking internet
then there'll be a russian internet and
a chinese internet
and we'll see what other internets might
emerge but i think
those will form kind of these closed
social spaces so
one way to think about that is that it's
a massive retreat in globalization
but i actually think that you know total
global cultural diversity will continue
to fall
there'll be a few alternative hegemonic
cultures
but the total cultural diversity in the
world will be smaller
and it'll be more long-distance
integration
so i still think we're actually on a
very very slow
centuries-long globalization trajectory
in terms of culture and basically modes
of economic production
i have to ask the question you know
we had this narrative of technological
progress
where the world used to be developed and
you know
divided into the first world and the
third world then it became divided into
the developed world and the developing
world
the term developing world implies these
countries are going to catch up with the
developed countries
i think we're going to have to introduce
new terminology
because i think a lot of countries are
post-industrial
in the negative sense so i think many
countries will have economies
that will actually recede to the state
of development we today call
developing we might then see a world
where
economically there's homogenization over
time right where
living standards in europe and north
america
uh and possibly even some corners of
east asia converge with those in the
rest of asia and latin america and
possibly even
the more advanced parts of africa not
because
there has been catch-up growth from
everyone so far only china has
really done impressive strong catch-up
growth but because there's a decline in
living standards in the former first
world
right and this then leads to a world
that's perhaps somewhat more
economically decentralized
but they're still winners and losers
it's just that they're kind of like
rotating at the table who's the
industrial power of this decade or this
these next few decades the idea of china
one day outsourcing its industrial base
and suffering urban blight
might seem ludicrous but it's far from
you know it's far
from an impossibility we saw the same in
europe
uh in britain right and we saw it in the
united states
and uh i would not at all be shocked if
there's a similar development
maybe there's something inherently
unstable about being a quote-unquote
developed society
so if there is something inherently
unstable
in being a quote unquote developed
society
that's a very pessimistic view i think
in that case we could see
a real receding of globalization
not just like this sort of like small
detour but
an actual failure of globalization right
cool all right
daniel do you want to ask your question
about ais
sure so uh i just had a question about
whether or not ais can discern live
players or ais can become live players
and kind of the background for this is
that increasingly as people
spend more time on the digital realm and
it
as psychographic data becomes more and
more fine-grained
it becomes harder and harder to actually
distinguish what is the root cause of
our initial
impulse to make a decision in one
direction or another so the whole ai
thing is being built is inbuilt into the
way the players are playing so
i just kind of want to hear you riff on
that
i think it might be possible to identify
live players using artificial
intelligence right because i think a lot
of these mass surveillance systems
are very good at picking up anomalies
so i think it could detect
relatively quickly unusual or anomalous
behavior now of course an anomaly could
be
it could be a positive outlier or a
negative outlier so i think
if you have something that detects live
players and it's automated an automated
system
it's gonna read and detect a bunch of
the people who are just doing weird
things for the sake of being weird and
there's no deeper wisdom there no deeper
advancement
and some of the smaller number of people
who are uh who are doing you know
poor doing uh unusual or exceptional
things
whether ai's can be live players i think
that just requires
general intelligence so that is then
rounded off to the question can
artificial intelligence be
generally intelligent so you know human
human-like in this sense
i don't see any theoretical reason why
it couldn't but i also see no reason
uh and so i'm assuming it can
uh i think we can have you know
human-level intelligence
but i see no particular reason to expect
it in the very near future
um just going off of your definition of
a live player being
a person or a group of people that are
able to do things that they haven't done
before
wouldn't you say that there are some ais
that are capable of
doing that new things that are currently
extant so
not generalized intelligence i would
agree they are
um in a narrow sense this might fit the
definition but doesn't fit the spirit of
the definition of this
experience because the spirit of the
definition is sort of like adaptation
right
this this ability to adapt to the novel
circumstances
in an unforeseen way and i don't think
there's any current narrow ai that can
like really adapt in this way
thank you thank you
excellent peter would you like to ask
your question
all right samuel what kind of questions
do live players ask
well that's a very good question um but
i think that
i think the the question to ask they ask
the kind of questions that allow you to
quickly figure out
where might lie this unusual
or very unexploited or very neglected
domain of deep knowledge
so knowledge that actually uh is not
just
some explicitly stated theoretical
material but some deep
unstated stuff that's you know in the
domain of intellectual dark matter
that's either you know tacit knowledge
or
it's trade secrets right so i think
that's one of the things they always
pursue i think they do pursue
this type of knowledge again it doesn't
have to live in books right
in fact it lives very well in
individuals
the second type of question life players
ask often is
well how does this system behave
and they probably don't even use the
term system but they will
ask questions about how things are done
and they'll ask people who are you know
uh very conventional so they will have a
passion for talking to the conventional
person
and they will have a passion for
discerning what life is like for the
normal individual or the everyday
individual
and partially because you know if you
can figure out how these very
predictable patterns work in your live
player
you can take some really impressive
shortcuts
and these are not shortcuts in the sense
of cheats
these are ways of achieving the goal
that fulfill both the spirit and the
letter of the law
but seem like they should be impossible
right and
not just in this legal sense but again
in this moral ethical sense this like
knowledge acquisition sense this
economic sense
any sense you want to think about it if
they observe the normal world
closely if they ask questions to figure
out what's happening in the normal world
and they try to see what is the abnormal
world what is the unknown what is the
hidden what is the unaware
and you can have this very wonderful
transfer of one
to the other right and that is immensely
immensely
profitable if i use a different analogy
so spirit or letter of the law is one
analogy profit is another analogy
you could say advantageous but then all
these words are problematic right they
already carry
they carry this kind of assumption of
either selfishness or selflessness
and i think it's uh it's more let's
let's settle on can be very advantageous
can be very empowering
right so they either pursue knowledge or
they pursue a certain kind of power
but when i say power i mean in this
sense that's not necessarily
self-centered
they they love shaping the world right
so all the questions are in service of
that
but it's very good to see you again
great and jen would you like to ask your
question
i'm sure hey summer um i really like
the article uh you wrote about youtube
and the knowledge revolution
um thank you been such a big part of my
life and also the examples you gave
um were really memorable for me um but i
also when i traveled i'll never forget
this example of seeing like a bunch of
like probably 16 year old monks in burma
and like wearing their
maroon robes um on their phone playing
like
a cooperative like fighting game um but
after they're done the game they all
just watched a shit ton of music videos
on youtube
while still in the monastery and it was
like lil wayne and jay-z
and like all that stuff like bugattis
and nice cars and this
um so i'm wondering in terms of what you
were saying about
the kind of homogenization that happens
what we are
your definition for what globalism will
play out i'm wondering what
you think about the role youtube has to
play in that and
um do you think it
do you think it ever has a localism
inflection point
um or does it kind of continue this way
uh i guess the analogy would be
everybody just had to have their local
english teacher but when all the english
teachers are together everybody can just
learn from like the best english teacher
in the world
and like what's the point of just
learning from subpar english teachers
if that analogy makes any sense i think
that
youtube is preponderately in this sense
a homogenizing
force but there is a counter force here
which is
it creates new niches right new niches
of knowledge sharing and i wrote about
this in the article
because the means through which to
record the world i mean i think very
quickly
these cameras will be more than
sufficient for recording even the most
high quality youtube videos right right
now
professional youtubers uh they usually
still buy purpose-made cameras
but for almost anything uh the you know
digital camera on your phone is
sufficient which means that we can
now record in fine detail action or
practice that the documentary filmmaking
team would have
never recorded right either for an
educational purpose like those 1950s
videos
or just for entertainment purpose like
1990s discovery channel
and this massive recording of these
things in everyday life
can preserve many practices in a way
that are
you know simply impossible if i go on
youtube i'm quite certain
i could find a channel and i've never
watched this channel but i'm sure it
exists
on uh you know traditional uh
traditional korean
bow carving like i have no reason to
think their bows are super
interesting but i bet that there are
some hobbyists that shoot bows and i bet
they're hobbyists who have tried to
recreate bows as they existed in korean
warfare
and i bet there there are youtube videos
of how to make those
so in a sense that cultural tradition is
preserved
in another sense it's divorced from
context
context it's sort of like european
martial arts um
we all know again east asian martial
arts but there was a set of european
martial arts that mostly went extinct
over the last 200 years or 300 years
because warfare in europe changed so
dramatically and was so oriented
around gunpowder weaponry that all these
ways of
fighting either with swords or just
wrestling in unusual ways were lost
and then recently there's been a
community that has revived those
practices
but this kind of wrestling like they're
not wrestling in taverns to settle
disputes nor are they fighting with
swords on the battlefield
so kind of the meaning of that has
changed
and nothing really prevents you from
picking up european martial arts
as a hobby in vietnam or vice versa
so i think there is homogenization
but hopefully the homogenization
preserves
some more optionality or variance right
so i think that that's how i would i
would propose that works
but then i would hear also point and
push a little bit back
uh because i think youtube doesn't you
know
it doesn't cross borders it's very easy
to have governments decide okay no
youtube here
we're only going to have russian youtube
or chinese youtube or american youtube
or european youtube
at this point maybe it sounds silly to
propose that the american and european
internets
might separate one day but they very
easily might
uh already with the enhanced privacy
rules of europe
when i go to europe and try to read the
la times the website informs me that
they
haven't yet figured out how to comply
with european privacy laws
so i just don't read it right when you
see a paywall or
this kind of announcement you don't read
it and you can imagine
that there would be also differences in
legal environment
say the us values free speech more
europe might value tolerance more
so you might have in fact a legal
incompatibility of
which videos are okay to upload versus
not
in the two large jurisdictions
if i so may ask a follow-up then of
course the the takeaway that comes to
mind for me then uh
is there's almost like a strong
bifurcation that you can imagine like
even in the way you're talking about
like kind of you get this optionality
it seems to me the bifurcation even with
that in youtube is
those who know how to search and use
search and those who just click
on the videos that show up on home
screen um
like i notice i use youtube i'm like go
carving i don't know i see an article
i'll google it
but my mom she like never types anything
to the search bar on youtube she's just
always
maybe some time ago in the beginning she
typed one indian tv show
and then just she just watches whatever
recommendations that happen well some
more interesting way that's convergence
with television no
television programming except the
programming is customized to you you're
not channel surfing it's it's delivered
to you on the basis of the information
gathered in the past
um i didn't really have more of a point
than that because i'm even thinking of
the same thing when you're saying like
the european internet will
will maybe potentially be different than
american internet imagine those with
sophistication
can use telegram or vpns and so on to
get access to all of the above
but there'll be always a tiny monarchy
well yeah
so i'm just wondering if that's a mental
model that
well the most natural comparison here is
the great firewall of china
even today in china it's very trivial to
access all
internet sites that you want it's
basically a very minor amount of
technical sophistication needed
but i remember hearing numbers that
about eight to ten percent of chinese
citizens ever do this
which is like a very small number you
know that's
politically in terms of mass
mobilization that's an irrelevant number
so if you buy this bifurcation happening
what what are the implications of it
because it's almost too easy for my mind
to be like bifurcation bad but i'm
curious
well i think it could be very good i
think it could be very good and not
intentionally good or designed with good
intent
but i think it might result in humanity
trying out several different things
and i think it's very useful for us to
try and have several cultural nodes
coexisting even if they're culturally
incompatible
uh because i think you know if humanity
will have
issues in the future it will be because
we have not tried enough
things right like we won't we won't have
learned the full possibilities i claim
that we do not know the full social
possibilities of what the technology of
2020 enables
nor do we know the full possibility of
where technology could develop
where social circumstance is different
right
and i don't think that there's like a
single technological attractor
i think that there are massive
contingencies right and i base this
you know this sort of let's call it an
informed guess
uh on the history of technology in our
own world where the printing press in
china versus the printing press in
europe
have a completely different sociological
effect right
because the preconditions when the
technology enters society are so
different
next question yeah uh key would you like
to ask your question
yeah hello hello
um thank you i did come in late i wanted
to
acknowledge that first but um the
question and answers
have been really informative so thank
you and
my question is related to when you spoke
of singularity earlier
um so i just was curious about
well speaking of what you just spoke
about just now which is
trying out um new things and
and seeing the bifurcation as in
in a good way not good intended way but
a way for
humans to try different things question
goes to
um what is your view or stance
or even maybe plan on pursuing
um singularity
well um i think that you know
the intelligence explosion version of
the singularity or the vengeance
singularity
uh these are like slightly different
concepts i'll just
learn i'll roll them together as in the
meaning of
this transcendence of the human
condition this mass
transformation with technology and an
explosion of intelligence information in
the world right
i'm i'm not sure whether
singularity as classically conceived is
sociologically viable i feel like
there's something
strange that happened where i feel like
we hit
ever stronger social headwinds
the closer we came to possibly achieving
a rate of progress that would achieve
the kind of compounding growth that
leads to singularity
now i know this is still this is a
little contrarian position i think the
default story is that we're actually
still progressing at a decent speed
uh but my my my claim would be that
there's something we don't quite
understand
about the interrelation between the
social structure
and intelligence
i think that there's something very
counterintuitive there
and it's a very much unclear so
assuming it is possible i would propose
that
the normal methods of increasing human
technological productivity you know
having the equivalent of conditions
where
intellectual golden age is possible
where there are some number of
exceptional
individuals co-creating possibly living
in one city possibly traveling between a
small number of cities
sharing innovation inspiring each other
producing on their own steam not needing
much permission from the rest of society
ever more empowered by information
technology
that that is the closest i can come to a
sort of singularity scenario
there's also a world where it's just
achieved through the design of like you
know deep mind or open ai succeed and
they build
you know a super intelligent machine in
and then that's the end of the human era
and we don't have to worry about it one
way or another
but i think that world for various
reasons is fairly unlikely
if i have to bet and you know i'm
willing to bet because i'm making
50-year plans instead of five-year plans
with my life and
with my intellectual explorations um i
think that that one
that route won't happen so i think it's
something like you know
maybe the renaissance uh plus
information technology
plus possibly very adaptive learning
systems
where my phone is you know both
collecting information about me
but i have the ability to use that data
uh and craft software on my own steam or
buy software on my own steam that's
trying to enhance my intelligence rather
than take advantage
of my predictability right so i think
even the current state of information
technology could be a significant boost
to our intelligence but
i do think it takes both the the human
side and the software side
i don't think we can drag humans much
more in one direction or another just
with software
though of course i admire you know
attempts like rome and so on to
to be better notetaking systems but yeah
hope that answers your question it does
it really does
can i ask one follow-up question of
course
um i just wanted to circle back to this
um social structure element that you
brought up
in the beginning of the answer could you
maybe expand a little bit on that and
why you think that's a factor
for um for sort of not
betting on the um
the deep mind ai open source type way of
thinking of the the future okay
um it's not immediately relevant
to artificial intelligence though in
some ways
it is where i will propose that
let's examine you know a naive
perspective might be
the more money you put into artificial
intelligence
the faster artificial intelligence
progress so if you went from
10 billion dollars to 500 billion
dollars
invested in ai you should have more
technological progress
but it's actually fairly easy to
possibly construct the opposite scenario
where 500 billion dollars in ai results
in
lots and lots of software being
reclassified as ai
projects there's an argument to be made
that this happened to
nanotechnology in the 1980s where
there was a firm argument that this
might be the future
you know molecular level machine
construction and so on
uh a concopia of you know rapidly
expanding material abundance so there
was a lot of government investment into
it
and resulted in a bunch of interesting
in themselves but
boring from the perspective of
nanotechnology
material science projects starting to
call themselves nanotech
so today there's probably like a
nanotechnology department
in many technical universities around
the world but the actual amount of
nanotechnology done is very low
and some of the people who might have
been attracted to the field of
nanotechnology
can't possibly compete with all these
nanotechnology phds
and it's a needle in a haystack if you
try to fund a real version of it
right so there's this surprising way
in which there are some ways you could
envision
vastly more resources being spent on
scientific progress that
doesn't enable it but chokes it off and
of course implicitly i think this is at
least
part of the reason why we've had such
disappointing returns
on investment in technology and science
for about 50 years
cool next question
we just got like so many good questions
in the chat
i think that's great this must mean i'm
answering them well if
if a q if that answer produces more
questions than it answers that's a great
answer
yes okay so um we have a plus one for
dan's question
uh it's about china dan would you like
to ask your question and then
uh we'll see how many more we can get to
before the end
um i'm not sure
it was about china um
i think it was on
was it the one that on anjon mentioned
about the uh
yeah oh is that
okay because there was an earlier
question i had about turchin about peter
turchin and cleo dynamics that one or
the uh
which one well he wanted to hear about
china i know you've said so many things
what do people want to hear which
question do you want to people want to
hear
well maybe the question can be restated
by the plus one
oh yeah yeah whoever gave me the plus
one uh yeah why don't you ask the
question
and i can clarify and jin you wanna
i just want dan to have his own session
next week
um okay well that confuses things even
more
um all right let's just go with the uh
let's go let's go to the china one then
okay so
um one of the i i made a comment and
this is what anjon
lashed onto and it was kind of riffing
off what you
uh mentioned earlier about tacit tacit
knowledge and you
had stated that uh um
that it's good that that that that the
different blocks that there's going to
be
there's not going to be a clear hegemon
we're going to have china and we're
going to have europe
we're going to have north america this
sort of thing and that
um different
political economic experiments and
technologies will be developed and legal
systems and so on and so forth will be
developed in these different areas
and then you mentioned something earlier
about tacit knowledge and i
and i agree that it's good
if these different um regions start
developing their own things
and i lived in china for 10 years so i'm
aware i lived on both sides of the great
firewall and i experienced the
difficulty of living out both sides of
the great fire well as well as it's
certainly inconvenient but i do think
the point about it not being
that difficult to avoid uh stands
because i've talked to to others who've
lived in china
and you'll get around yeah yeah a vpn
and easily you can get around it um
it can be a hassle at times but my my
point is that most
most chinese people for example are not
fluent in english
yes and that's kind of the the language
barrier
the language barrier and there's not
only a language barrier there's a huge
culture there
and this gets to the your point about
the tacit knowledge
there's even a big culture barrier
between europe
and and kind of the neo-liberal
libertarian capitalist
american capitalist as well so um
my point is i think it's great that
these different experiments are
happening
but there's an ins i would argue that
there is an insufficient
number of people that are bi-cultural
or bilingual sorry
um to take advantage
of these different experiments so we
have these wonderful
experiments that are going on in the
world but
the the different parts of the world
can't really take advantage of them
because an
insufficient number of people
um in each culture is
kind of a dual citizen or dual you know
bicultural
to to bring that into the culture and
they've bifurcated or trifurcated
to such a degree and we're so polarized
that there's also that that comes into
play as well so i was wondering if you i
think this is this is very much
true in the sense that it's true that we
benefit massively for more people that
can in fact be bicultural that not only
cross
a language care barrier but as you noted
this much more fundamental cultural
barrier
like i guarantee you there is a culture
shock for anyone that moves from
new york to san francisco from san
francisco to new york it's subtle
they don't want to call it a culture
shock but it is a culture shock and you
go through the list of like you know the
symptoms of culture shock which are
sometimes physiological symptoms you
might have a fever for example
um they experience it and of course they
always complain about leaving new york
right so
there's that they are somehow aware that
they have been molded by one city
and even though we all speak you know
all speak english a lot of us are
immigrants
most people are american citizens it's
so different
so everything said there extends also to
britain
extends to germany so within the western
world
and let alone japan which is
economically integrated but culturally
not integrated at all
and in fact japan also has a language
barrier and people might not realize
that actually
english fluency is not that good in in
japan
and of course japanese fluency is
non-existent in the united states
this leads me to say something
rather interesting right imagine that
these are sort of
seeds we've planted well we don't have
to we don't have to immediately harness
all of them
right there's a bifurcation or
trifurcation or
fragmentation of the world but often
people learn the most
or most inspired by civilizations that
reach the end stage of their existence
uh it is byzantine scholars fleeing
the byzantine empire and you know arab
scholars
you know teaching in cordoba in spain
that sort of bring the renaissance
to europe this transition of
ancient greek knowledge significantly
relies on the end of the byzantine world
and i would also argue that the advances
in artificial intelligence that we did
see in the united states
were the result of soviet emigres from
the 1990s
how many places that have top quality
engineers and scientists and
mathematicians who would have had the
berlin wall never fallen
been soviet mathematicians and so on
there's also like
a deeper intellectual legacy with the
pre-history of artificial intelligence
that i won't go into um and then i can
give another example
you know this is a possibly you know
obviously you know
nazi germany was this terrible terrible
country terrible regime
however america's rocket science comes
from there
and was operation paper clipped it bins
that brings
verner von braun and the other rocket
scientists to the united states and
enables the space program
so often when a societal experiment
either successful or unsuccessful is
essentially over or starts falling apart
the fragments of it or the refugees of
it will be extremely productive in a new
culture
if only there's anywhere at all to go uh
in fact i can give you a more
interesting analogy where arguably the
german world had two stages of collapse
first is
the rise of the nazis causes a lot of
the intellectually most productive
people to flee for the united states
and then the fall of the nazis causes
the few remaining intellectually
productive people to flee
and this is why germany is like perhaps
good in industry but is not the
intellectual frontier anymore
and it just was the intellectual
frontier for about 100 years
from about 1830 onwards to about 1930.
cool next next question can we do like
two more questions i know it's at the
hour perfect
great okay so tyson would you like to
ask your question
sure thank you okay so a question
yes uh so have cities reached a point of
diminishing returns as far as their
ability to extract innovation and
productivity
from people and will significant amounts
of people move away from cities into
rural areas to pursue
a new way of living and if so
you think it's likely there will be
major efforts from the elites
to resist or slow this shift in this
migration and then if so um like
maybe any thoughts about what to do
about that or just
yeah how you think about that it's a
very good question
i hope the answer is no because if the
answer is yes
i just believe this means that you know
american civilization has entered
terminal decline
i can't think of a single deurbanization
in the last 10 000 years
and no cities are deeply problematic
objects right cities are often death
traps
they're often places of misery uh
they're often places of violence and
instability
but i can't think of a single case where
deurbanization happened
i can think of many cases where there is
an expansion where there's a large
rural population where previously it was
just a hunter-gatherer population
right say you know colonizing of the
americas right
but this this isn't the the end of
cities or the cities being out competed
uh usually it's the case that cities
monopolize the best opportunities for
themselves
so if we are seeing mass de-urbanization
in the us
i don't think this is due to like you
know there being such
amazing opportunities in the countryside
it's because the cities themselves
even after having hogged all the best
opportunities in society
don't have much to offer so it's sort of
like growth has been completely choked
off
it's not just zero-sum games because
zero-sum games can maintain cities i
think
at least for a while it's negative some
games
so people flee right the only winning
move
if the only winning move for the game of
society
is not to play that's the situation
where you see the urbanization
and if the only winning move is not to
play well then eventually there'll be a
bank run
so i hope that's not the case and i also
think that there will be
de-urbanization of some american cities
for example
i would not be surprised if chicago
eventually converges with
uh other hollowed-out uh great lake
cities such as detroit
and i would not be surprised if new york
significantly stagnates
but i don't think its population is
going to go down
uh i also would not be that surprised
if you see a complete failure of either
san francisco or seattle
so again i think the primary the primary
prediction i would make the likeliest
basin you know evidence seems to be in
the outcome of a stable san francisco
and a growing and technologically
innovative seattle
though the san francisco is kind of like
a finance center i think it becomes the
finance center of the west coast
uh including with its own stock exchange
as uh
there's a new one being set up and with
various financial instruments that will
be
distant uh legal descendants of the
venture capital industry
great and our final question from the
medic
caper hey
so i have a thought that uh language
might naturally decay and lose its
semantic meaning
so it would move from expressive and
sacred
uh to instrumental and profane um
i think i think this problem is solved
in pre-modern societies through
ritual is one way it can also be
violence but in modern societies we've
kind of
tried to replace all that with uh with
growth like economic growth or
technological
innovation um and i was i was wondering
if you think
uh this is i guess sufficient to uh
to reify language because if if you have
um no if there's no like hooks for
language to dig into in reality
it just starts sliding around and you
get people um you know
you talk about scripts right people are
repeating scripts to get what they
they want but the scripts are they're
meaningless they're uh they're
interchangeable right
well yes um
the scripts are interchangeable
but just because you know i think i
think behaviorism is is a relatively
nega is a reasonably negative way of
viewing the human condition
but something along the lines of well
does the flight of a bird have meaning
so a lot of these scripts are
meaningless but adaptive
if this makes sense and they do differ
to each other from each other
in their adaptivity
yeah well there is a like a physical
layer of uh
objective reality which uh you know you
that's a problem you can run into i mean
yeah so either you raiify language
through
some kind of ritual or you just get into
serious shit and then and then you have
to manage it right
well i think i think language has a
wonderful ability to reinvent itself
where basically
subcultural groups might actually have
higher information
density language right now than
mainstream society
because the subculture uses stuff that's
not visible
or intelligible to the outside to
communicate
highly contextual information meanwhile
say
i think for example like if you could in
information theory
measure the amount of information that
is conveyed
through the course of a normal political
debate or
through the course of a brief
conversation on wall street today
i'm not sure a lot of information is
exchanged i think a lot of very complex
verbal behavior happens but i think very
little information is passed through
and if i look at some twitter
subcultures i see immense amounts of
information
passed through you know the 280
characters available
so i sort of am optimistic in the sense
that meaning can be rescued
if only by retreating to the esoteric or
retreating to the straussian
or retreating to the subrosa layer
cool yeah well i'm not i'm not saying
meaning is uh
it's hopeless i'm not saying that i'm
saying uh are we sort of at a lack
for for means of um
of ensuring this connection between
language and meaning like is there
oh yes yes no no question about it
language right now
and communication and the epistemic
commons are
really compromised and i applaud any and
all efforts to improve the
epistemic commons and the communication
commons
it's just deeply necessary
infrastructure for our society
okay thank you for your question was
that was that the last one
that was the last one and thank you so
much for staying a little bit over to
answer all these great questions
great thank you for that of course thank
you so much and we'll see you again next
week
and i will just do a little bit of a
up regulating of some of the events that
we have coming up tomorrow
at the wisdom gym we have the psycho
technology playground with bonita roy
at 10 a.m we have collective presenting
with ria beck
at noon and we have socratic speed
dating with yours truly
ravenconnelly at 7pm uh you can register
at the stoa.ca we also have the
recurring sense making series the dark
stoa with pat ryan
tomorrow at 8 30. i think that this is
the last of the first season
so don't miss that one and then for a
one-off session we have
who's sensing the sensemakers with brent
cooper
brent cooper is a vocal critic
of the sense-making web and he's coming
to
address this important question so that
will be at 5
30 eastern time hope to see you all
there
and if you would like to give the stoa a
gift
you can visit us at the stowa dot ca
gift and thank you all so much
and we'll see you next time thanks sama
bye everyone